<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-16T21:02:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">RCDS College Advice</title><subtitle>Built by and for RCDS students</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Basics of the College Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/the_basics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Basics of the College Process" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:06-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:06-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/the_basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/the_basics.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;vocabulary&quot;&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;admissions&quot;&gt;Admissions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EA - Early action.  If you apply early action to a school, you are not required to attend it.  It basically just means that you can get some of your applications out earlier in the year (typically November 1).  You can still wait to hear back from your RD schools before deciding if you will go to a school you got into EA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ED - Early decision.  If you apply early decision to a school, you are required to attend if you get in.  You can only apply ED to one school for obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;REA - Restricted early action.  Similar to early action but you can only apply early to that one school as well as state schools.  You are not required to attend schools you get into REA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RD - Regular decision.  You can apply to as many schools as you want to regular decision.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rolling admissions.  You can apply anytime to a school with rolling admissions and get their decision back relatively soon after.  You can still wait until late in the year to make your decision.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deferral.  If you are deferred from a school ED or EA, you can still apply regular decision.  You are neither accepted or rejected, just pushed into the regular decision pool of applications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waitlisted.  If you are waitlisted at a college, some students who were accepted will have to choose to go to other colleges in order for you to be accepted.  Some colleges waitlists have extremely low acceptance rates, but this depends on the college.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common Application: application that applicants may use to apply to 20 colleges or university. This is where the colleges look at your application&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your Personal essay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extracurriculars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic information about yourself and your family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;logistical-items&quot;&gt;Logistical items&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow sheet.  Your yellow sheet is the sheet kept by the college counseling office that keeps track of all of the colleges you are applying to and their deadlines so they know where to send your scores and transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naviance. Naviance is a website that you are able to research colleges and where you can make your official college list. It is connected with your college counselors so they are able to see where you are thinking about applying.  You can search colleges and see where people in the past applied an&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;general-tips&quot;&gt;General Tips&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to have a list of schools you want to apply to by the start of summer.  Supplements for most colleges come out August 1st&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do your best to finish taking standardized test before senior year.  However not the end of the world if you don’t.  KEEP GRINDING!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be really hard to keep working as hard as you can when it feels like it’s never ending, but in the end it will pay off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay on your own path.  During this process, it’s really easy to compare yourself to your friends or other people who are applying but just try to block everyone else out.  Your process is going to be different than your friends so don’t compare yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Vocabulary</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Researching Colleges</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/researching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Researching Colleges" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:05-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:05-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/researching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/researching.html">&lt;p&gt;Before paying for flights or looking for hotels make sure you RESEARCH every school you think you are interested into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research what is important to you. Some might be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;School spirit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Majors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Internships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Class size&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Aid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extracurriculars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you research all of the above and are happy with your results apply to those schools&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do not necessarily have to visit the school!  The college process is expensive!!! You have to take into consideration everything when you are deciding on the right school for you.  You do not need to visit all of the schools you applied to. Transportation is very very expensive, as well as the hotel you stay in when visiting campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, my mom would not allow me to visit all of the schools on my list. In fact, I only visited one.  Once you get into the schools, then you can go visit the school. Otherwise you wasted a trip and money visiting a school you are not accepted to.  Once you visit 3-4 schools they all start to look the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because all of your friends are visiting schools does not mean you have to. Don’t feel pressured or bad because you didn’t. It’s a normal thing not to visit all of the schools that you are applying to. Don’t feel pressured to visit all of your schools&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Before paying for flights or looking for hotels make sure you RESEARCH every school you think you are interested into.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing Essays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/essays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing Essays" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:04-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:04-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/essays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/essays.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Talking About College</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/talking_about_college.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talking About College" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:03-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:03-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/talking_about_college</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/talking_about_college.html">&lt;p&gt;College is a hard conversation to have and everyone will be asking you about it.  Here is how to have some tough conversations with different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;with-yourself&quot;&gt;With yourself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be honest. What are your strengths and what are your weaknesses? Have this conversation with yourself before hand and don’t hold back. This will help you begin to think about your future and where you see yourself in 5 years. Be honest about your level of independence, maturity and the support systems you depend on. When you’re researching, analyze what are your reach, fit and safety schools are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be self-challenging. Ideally, this is where you will be spending the next four years of your life. Think about the environment that you see yourself thriving in, the people you’d like to be surrounded with, and push yourself to try something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be patient. You might not figure out what your perfect college is and you might not know what you want to study. Give yourself time to research and ask questions. But don’t force yourself to apply early decision somewhere and don’t force yourself to fall in love with a school. Everyone’s process is different; don’t set expectations for yourself, just go with the flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;with-your-family&quot;&gt;With your family&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communicate to your family members on what kind of support you will need from them throughout this process. Tell them about your goals and aspirations so that they can help you navigate colleges. However, remember that this is your process and it is your future you are working towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone will ask you where you want to go. This might create some pressure and you need to learn how to deal with it. Either be honest and tell them your plans, or have a backup school that you mention to avoid awkwardness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;your-friendspeers&quot;&gt;Your friends/peers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t compare yourself to others. Your peers may have different aspirations and desires for themselves. Don’t take on their expectations as the ultimate ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">College is a hard conversation to have and everyone will be asking you about it. Here is how to have some tough conversations with different people.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interviews</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/interviews.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interviews" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:02-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:02-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/interviews</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/interviews.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s no one secret that’ll cause you to completely nail any interview thrown at you.  Every interview and interviewer will bring something different to the table, but there are some key things you might want to do to help give your interviewer the best possible impression of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re scheduling your interview, make sure to use proper email educate.  It’s so obvious, but misspelling words can be costly on your first impression.  Also remember to reply with quote just to make their lives easier.  Hopefully they’ll take the initiative in laying out some possible times to meet with them, but if they ask that you provide some time you’re free, try to give many options as abstractly as possible “I’m free on Saturdays in the morning and late afternoon as well as all day Sunday.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t overdress or underdress.  Look nice, but you don’t want to come across as needy or pretentious with your outfit.  You should dress up, but if you stick out like a sore thumb at whatever location you’re meeting your interviewer, it’s probably a good sign that you’ve overdressed.  For example, if you’re interviewing in a coffee shop, a suit and tie might be a bit overkill, but a nice sweater or button-down can blend in without looking overdressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be ready to answer the “why X college” question.  There is always something specific about this college that is unlike most other colleges for you to talk about.  It can be something like a specific program, but if it is, make sure to explain how that relates to your goals as a whole or the college as a whole.  For example, “The main thing that got me interested in this college is their dual engineering and entrepreneurship program, because there really aren’t many other colleges where I can learn both disciplines to such a rigorous extent to prepare me to launch my own company when I graduate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be ready to ask questions about the college.  Interviewers will almost always end the interview with, “so in the last few minutes I was wondering if you had any questions for me.”  These should be things you can’t get from the admission website.  For example, “it’s really hard to get a sense of the culture of the school without meeting people who went there and I frankly haven’t had the ability to talk to many people who have, so I was wondering if you could give any insights on what the school culture is like.”  Feel free to ask about the interviewer’s time in college as well.  Remember, these are people who voluntarily interview high schoolers in order to benefit their university, meaning that they really enjoyed their time and would love any chance to reminisce on it.  Asking them about their time is a surefire way to get them more engaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-to-bring&quot;&gt;What to bring&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See what the college’s policy is on resumes.  9 times out of 10 they would like one or at the very least would take one.  It should look clean, ideally stored in a folder, and no more than a page front and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring a pen and a notepad.  Maybe you’ll have something insightful to write down or maybe not.  At the very least, you’ll look prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it into a show and tell.  If you have an object or some pictures that really capture your high school career, bring it to your interview.  Maybe it’s your art portfolio or something you built; either way it’s great to facilitate discussion.  If you’re showing them pictures on your phone, make a new album of pictures exclusively for interviews just in case they try to scroll through your photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-interview-itself&quot;&gt;The interview itself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be early.  The worst possible situation is trying to show up 5 minutes before the interview and being stuck looking for parking.  Give yourself at least fifteen minutes beforehand to make sure you’re near where you need to be with a comfortable amount of time to spare.  Being even a little late looks bad and first impressions are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t psych yourself out.  It’s just a conversation.  Almost all interviewers are incredibly pleasant people to talk to and they just want to get a good sense of you.  Talk about yourself and the things you’re passionate about.  Have a good body of anecdotes that you can bring up for certain situations.  Don’t memorize them but be ready to pull one out and tell it at a moments notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever catch yourself stretching the truth a little bit, don’t panic.  Try to move onto another topic or anecdote in a way that’s not too forced so that you don’t dig yourself into a hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be conscious of your body language.  Don’t slouch into your chair or fidget with anything.  Try to mirror your interviewer’s posture if relevant.  In other words, if they’re leaning back you might not want to sit all the way up and towards the table.  Do try to maintain eye contact whenever possible, especially if they’re the ones talking.
Don’t feel too bad about telling them your accomplishments.  False modesty is something many of us use in our daily lives.  If you did something awesome, tell them that.  If you feel like you might be bragging, you’ll have to read the conversation to see how to talk about your accomplishments.  A good rule of thumb is that if it directly answers their question and is completely true, then it’s not bragging.
Start and end the conversation with firm handshakes and “thank you”s.  It’s not the biggest deal, but a good first impression is always important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;after-the-interview&quot;&gt;After the interview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Send a thank you email.  It isn’t the biggest gesture but it’s always appreciated.  These should be short and relevant to your discussion.  Maybe mention that you’re grateful for them offering their opinion on X aspect of the school.  It can be brief, maybe 3 or so sentences, but it can have a large effect as not all applicants send these.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There’s no one secret that’ll cause you to completely nail any interview thrown at you. Every interview and interviewer will bring something different to the table, but there are some key things you might want to do to help give your interviewer the best possible impression of you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealing With Rejection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/dealing_with_rejection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealing With Rejection" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:01-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:01-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/dealing_with_rejection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/dealing_with_rejection.html">&lt;p&gt;It takes about roughly two months to receive a decision letter. They’re usually posted online or by letter. This can be very nerve racking, but reacting to any outcome in the right way is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acceptance&quot;&gt;Acceptance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it is important to be happy and show how enthusiastic you are if you are accepted. It’s great to celebrate with family and friends. However, others might not have the same outcome as you, so your enthusiasm can hurt others, especially if others applied to the same school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t exploit your acceptance to everyone, but the people who you know will take your acceptance in a positive way. You never know what is going on in another’s life our their college experience, so going out of your way to talk about your acceptance can be seen as annoying or rude.  Try your best to avoid talking about your acceptance with people who you know applied to the same college and don’t ask others about their decision outcomes unless they told you to ask beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rejections&quot;&gt;Rejections&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rejection can be tough, but DO not worry and DO not get sad because there are so many other schools. Wherever you end up you will love and you can’t be let down by another’s school’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw out that letter and make the most of the one you are accepted to because college is all about what you make of it.  If someone asks you about if you were accepted or rejected, answer on what your feelings regarding this situation are. If you are an open book then illustrate the decision&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to exploit your rejection just respond saying “I’m keeping my college decisions to myself,” and they should understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;deferral&quot;&gt;Deferral&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hang in there. You are not accepted nor rejected, but you are just put into the regular decision pool. Take this as a positive because the school still thinks highly of you, but couldn’t accept you early. You still have the same chance you did before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be tough waiting another two or so months, but it is better than being rejected. You still are in the running!!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It takes about roughly two months to receive a decision letter. They’re usually posted online or by letter. This can be very nerve racking, but reacting to any outcome in the right way is important.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Extra Tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/extra_tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extra Tips" /><published>2019-01-15T11:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T11:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/extra_tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2019/01/15/extra_tips.html">&lt;p&gt;Yes you will freak out, yes might have some breakdowns, yes you may cry and turn into a sassy and rude teenager but everything will be okay.  Everyone will end up where they are supposed to be and college isn’t the end of the world.  We’re in a community that values college to such an unhealthy degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to soothing music&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to write at least one draft of personal essay and some supplements in the summer.  You’ll thank yourself later if you get ahead in the summer.  If you can, just bang out like five personal essays and pick the best one.  Oftentimes you’ll be able to use the other ones for supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental health days are valid.  If you need to take time off of school for yourself, do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meet with your teachers and tell them how you are feeling. They are understanding, amazing people who will help you in any way they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take notes during information sessions (when a college representative  comes to visit RCDS)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yes you will freak out, yes might have some breakdowns, yes you may cry and turn into a sassy and rude teenager but everything will be okay. Everyone will end up where they are supposed to be and college isn’t the end of the world. We’re in a community that values college to such an unhealthy degree.</summary></entry></feed>